Konvitz, Milton R. Papers /4039
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Civil Liberties Educational Foundation, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    1957, 1960-1962. Correspondence with the Executive Directors of Civil Liberties Educational Foundation regarding an annotated civil and political rights bibliography for high school students. Konvitz was a member of Civil Liberties Educational Foundation National Study Group to improve the teaching of the Bill of Rights (July 20, 1961).
  - Ching, Cyrus S., Fund, 1956-1959 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    1956, 1959. Correspondence with several people including Dean Catherwood and Louis G. Silverberg, Director of Information of the National Labor Relations Board, regarding the establishment of the proposed Cyrus S. Ching Fund at Cornel. The income from the fund was to be distributed to Industrial and Labor Relations graduate students with selection based on academic promise or performance, financial need or research ability. List of contributors to the fund.
  - Clark, Grenville, 1966-1980 (Box 10, Folder 20)
    1966, 1970-1971, 1973-1980. Letter to Konvitz from Grenville Clark in which he comments on the United Nations. Other routine reports and letters of the Grenville Clark Fund.
  - Cohen, Elliot - Commentary, 1946-1959 (Box 10, Folder 21)
    1946-1952, 1954-1959. Correspondence with several editors especially Elliot Cohen, of Commentary: A Jewish Review. Detailed and lengthy discussions between Konvitz and Commentary staff regarding publications by Konvitz and several other authors. Critical, substantive comments by Konvitz on articles and book reviews. Copies of Konvitz's letters to the editors of Commentary; some letters are in response to those written by readers in reaction to Konvitz's articles - a wide range of subjects are touched upon in relation to pieces being reviewed or considered for publication.
  - Cohen, Frank, 1946-1950 (Box 10, Folder 22)
    1946-1947, 1949-1950. Correspondence with Mister Frank Cohen. A series of letters from Cohen mailed to American Zionists to convey his first-hand impression of Palestine, and raise many primary issues regarding American Jews' relation with Palestine. The letters provide much detail regarding the conditions in Palestine during the 1940s, the economic and political problems in Palestine, and the issues confronting American Zionists which needed to be resolved in regard to their aid to Jews in Palestine. Konvitz responds positively to some of the issues raised by Cohen. Also personal correspondence.
  - Cohen, Lucy [Misses Felix S. Cohen], 1946-1959 (Box 10, Folder 23)
    1946-1956, 1958-1959. Correspondence with Lucy Cohen regarding Konvitz's efforts to get Ethical Systems and Legal Ideals by her deceased husband reprinted. Doctor Konvitz wrote the prefatory note to the reprinted edition. Also correspondence with Lucy Cohen regarding other works by Cohen and personal matters. Most of the correspondence in the folder is with Doctor Felix S. Cohen, Ex-Associate Solicitor of the Interior Department. There is a great deal of detailed correspondence between Konvitz and Cohen regarding arrangements to complete several chapters of Professor Morris R. Cohen's (Felix Cohen's deceased father's) unfinished manuscript The Development of American Thought and regarding personal matters.
  - Cohen, Lucy [Misses Felix S. Cohen], 1960-1964 (Box 10, Folder 24)
    [1960- ] 1960-1961, 1964. Correspondence with Lucy Cohen about The Legal Conscience by Felix S. Cohen. Konvitz wrote a review of the book for the January 1961 Columbia Law Review. Also personal correspondence.
  - Cohn, Haim, 1967-1979 (Box 10, Folder 25)
    1967, 1970-1979. Correspondence with Justice Haim Cohn, the Supreme Court of Israel regarding scholarly and personal matters. The correspondence includes detailed information about the work and scholarly interests of both men. Konvitz and Cohen discuss Spinoza and Maimonides in several letters. Also correspondence on the subject of imprisonment from both biblical and practical perspectives. Also discussion on the intellectual activities of both men.
  - Colin, David, 1949-1950 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Personal correspondence with Doctor David H. Colin, New York University Department of economics, regarding the publication of Colin's manuscript on unemployment insurance in New York.
  - [P.F.] Collier and Son Corporation, 1956-1957 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    Correspondence with William T. Couch, Editor-in-Chief regarding the preparation of articles by Konvitz on Civil Rights and Civil Liberties for the 1957 Collier's Encyclopedia Year Book
  - Columbia University - Center for Research - American Liberties [A. Westin], 1972-1976 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    Correspondence with Professor Alan F. Westin, Editor of The Civil Liberties Review, regarding periodical and personal matters; and letters with reference to the Center for Research and Education in American Liberties. Columbia University and Teachers College (1965 and 1968)
  - COM-CZ, 1956-1966 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    1956-1957, 1960-1966. Correspondence with Doctor Harold Weisberg, Chairman of the B'nai B'rith Commission on Adult Jewish Education. Professor Konvitz agrees to serve on the Commission's Advisory Board (May 23, 1966). Correspondence with John Conyers, Junior, United States House of Representatives Committee on Judiciary regarding the nomination of J.P. Coleman to the Fifth Circuit Court of Appeals (July 26, 1965). Correspondence with Samuel Caplan, Editor of Congress Weekly, on Konvitz's article and press release concerning the stoning of a church in Jerusalem. Correspondence with Robert E. Cushman, National Historical Publications Commission, on academic and personal matters.
  - Commission on Civil Rights, 1958-1975 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    1958-1960, 1963, 1974-1975. Correspondence with Gordon M. Tiffany, Staff Director, with enclosures relating to Konvitz's plans to attend the Commission's hearings on housing in New York City as a member of the New York State Advisory Committee (January 7, 1959). In a memorandum to President Malott, Provost Atwood, Dean Catherwood, and Dean Thoron, Konvitz informs them of his appointment to the New York State Advisory Committee of the Federal Commission on Civil Rights and that the New Jersey State Civil Rights Commission has approved the report that Konvitz drafted as the chairman of the State commission that investigated administrative and enforcement procedures under the New Jersey Fair Employment Practice and Civil Rights Acts (November 20, 1958). Letter from Senator Thomas C. Hennings, Junior, Chairman of the Subcommittee on Constitutional Rights, asking Konvitz for a statement of his views regarding legal or constitutional questions or problems that are raised by present-day methods and uses of wiretapping and eavesdropping. Hennings comments that with Konvitz's permission the statement would probably be incorporated into the record of future wiretapping and eavesdropping hearings (October 2, 1958). Also routine correspondence from the New York State Advisory Committee of the Federal Civil Rights commission on which Konvitz served.
  - Commission on European Jewish cultural Reconstruction, 1947 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Minutes of the June 4, 1947 annual meeting of the Commission of which Konvitz was a member
  - Commission on Formal Jewish Studies, 1972-1974 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    In letters to the editors of Judaism and Commentary, Doctor Konvitz explains that he accepted the chairmanship of a Commission on Formal University Jewish Studies Programs that was appointed by Doctor Nahum Goldmann, Chairman of the Memorial Foundation for Jewish Culture. The Memorial Foundation appointed the Commission because it had decided to contribute a substantial amount of money each year to help establish and develop Jewish Studies Programs in colleges and universities. Konvitz prepared the report which was subsequently adopted by the Board of Directors of the Memorial Foundation.
  - Commission on Government Security (Washington, District of Columbia), 1955 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    Copies of letters that Konvitz sent to Simon E. Sobeloff, Solicitor General of the Department of Justice, and to Dean Irving M. Ives regarding Konvitz's possible appointment to the Commission on Government Security (August 15, 1955)
  - Committee on Supreme Court Decisions, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    Konvitz agrees to serve on the Association of American Law Schools Committee on Supreme Court Decisions (February 26, 1964).
  - Committee to Maintain Separation of Church and State, 1948-1949 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    Correspondence regarding Konvitz's speaking engagement for the committee
  - Common Ground, 1946-1987 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    1946-1951 [1987]. Correspondence with M. Margaret Anderson, editor of Common Ground, published by the Common Council for American Unity. Doctor Konvitz wrote a column titled "The Pursuit of Liberty" for several issues in which he discussed important civil liberties cases and placed the development in civil liberties in the context of American jurisprudence (December 20, 1948). Correspondence with Read Lewis, Executive Director of the Common Council. Konvitz provides detailed comments on a draft outline on the prevention of discrimination and the protection of minorities prepared for the United Nations Commission on Human Rights (October 27, 1948). Other correspondence with Anderson regarding substantive concerns about Konvitz's department (for example, what should be covered) and about the periodical.
  - Communications Workers of America, 1956-1957 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    Correspondence with Sylvia B. Gottleib, Research Department Director regarding the establishment of a grant or fellowship at Cornell for the support of graduate research on the telephone industries in the United States and Canada
  - Conference on Jewish Material Claims against Germany, Incorporated, 1960-1964 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    [1960- ] 1961- 1964. Routine correspondence with various officers of the conference regarding Konvitz's evaluation of applicants for scholarships
  - Conference on Jewish Material Claims Against Germany, Incorporated - Judah J. Shapiro, 1954-1959 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    Correspondence with Doctor Judah J. Shapiro, Department of Cultural and Educational Reconstruction and other officers regarding Konvitz's evaluation of applicants for the scholarships. Also correspondence with Shapiro regarding religious issues and Cornell faculty appointments and Shapiro's response to Konvitz's comments about Shapiro's view of Judaism (September 12, 1956).
  - Conference on Methods, 1946-1953 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    1946-1947, 1949, 1953. Correspondence on the Conference on Methods in Philosophy and the Sciences in which Konvitz was involved as Secretary-Treasurer (1945 ad 1946) and as a member of the Executive Committee (1944-1945 and 1946-1947).
  - Consumers League of New York, 1947-1948 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Cooley, Thomas M. II, 1948-1949 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    Correspondence with Thomas M. Cooley II, a Washington, District of Columbia attorney regarding a memorandum by Cooley in the Kaminer case. Konvitz comments on Cooley's memorandum. Also detailed correspondence between Konvitz and Cooley regarding the latter's review of Doctor Konvitz's book, The Alien and the Asiatic in American Law, in the November 1947 Columbia Law Review.
  - Cooper Union, 1947-1948 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    Correspondence with Johnson E. Fairchild, Head of the Division of Social Philosophy at Cooper Union, regarding Konvitz's talk on "The Multidimensionality of History" for the Cooper Union Forum Sunday Series of 1948-1949
  - Cooperman, Hayse., 1946-1961 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    1946-1948, 1952-1953, 1957-1961. Correspondence with Doctor Hayse Cooperman regarding personal matters.
  - Cornell Civil Liberties Committee, 1947 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Council of Europe, 1963-1972 (Box 11, Folder 21)
    Press releases: copy of 1963 letter from Konvitz to Mister e. Harremoes, regarding the council of Europe establishing Cornell University Libraries as one of its depositories in the United States.
  - Council of Jewish Federations and Welfare Funds - Personal, 1950-1955 (Box 11, Folder 22)
    1950-1952, 1955. Correspondence with Benjamin B. Rosenberg, Director Field Service, regarding routine matters of the Technical Advisory Committee of the Committee on Community Organization of which Konvitz was a member.
  - Council of Jewish Federations and Welfare Funds, 1969-1970 (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - Cushman Book Manuscripts, 1957 (Box 11, Folder 24)
    Letters from Professor Quincy Wright and Professor George Catlin, McGill University, regarding their contributions to the Cushman Festschrift. Copy of Catlin's "On Freedom" with revisions.
  - D, 1974 (Box 11, Folder 25)
    1947-1958, 1960, 1962, 1974. Correspondence from various people supporting Professor Konvitz's "A Letter to David Daiches" (April 1951). Memorandum from Konvitz to Daiches asking him to join the Academic Committee for the Hebrew University (February 10, 1947). Cordial letter from Daiches regarding Konvitz's plans to visit him while he is at Cambridge (October 8, 1952). Correspondence with John Daniels, researcher and author in social- economic areas such as labor-management relations, regarding routine academic and theological concerns. Daniels comments on his religious philosophy (February 7, 1949). Copies of articles by Daniels. Correspondence with Professor C.E. De Kiewiet, Acting President of Cornell University regarding scholarly and personal matters. De Kiewiet comments on some of Konvitz's articles and explains why he considers himself to be secular in his thinking (1949). De Kiewiet mentions that he would prefer to be writing and researching (June 18, 1949). Correspondence with Harry N. Rosenfield, Commissioner of the Displaced Persons Commission, regarding Konvitz's efforts to stimulate interest among Cornell professors in conducting research using the records of the Commission (December 1951-February 1952). Correspondence with William H Donnelly, standing Master of the Superior Court of New Jersey Chancery Division, regarding routine personal matters. Correspondence with Albert Dorskind, United States Court of Appeals. On the Lapides case (May 31, 1949). Correspondence with Garry De Yong, founder of the first American Atheist University (the Minnesota Institute of Philosophy) and the American Atheist Church regarding Yong's civil rights suit, concerning religious freedom, against the Minnesota Highway department. Konvitz provides Yong with references for finding quotations with respect to First Amendment Freedoms and especially freedom of religion (August 22, 1974).
  - D - Personal, 1948-1964 (Box 11, Folder 26)
    1948, 1953-1956, 1960-1964. Correspondence with Samuel H. Daroff, President of the American Jewish League for Israel, regarding League matters of interest to Konvitz as a member of the League's Board of Directors. Routine personal correspondence with Doctor Henry David, head of the Office of Science Resources Planning of the National Science Foundation (February 1964). Routine personal correspondence with Miguel De Capriles, Dean of New York University School of Law (November 13, 1964). Letter from C.W. de Kiewiet, President of the University of Rochester and former Acting President of Cornell, regarding personal matters. De Kiewiet discusses George Sabine and a tragic event in Cape Town in which he was the last person to speak with someone (Davie) before he died "in battle if ever man did." De Kiewiet describes the day on which his friend died as one of "a great imaginative act of defiance and faith" (February 6, 1961). Correspondence with Professor Lincoln Reis, Chairman of the Colleges and Universities Committee of the Democratic State Committee, regarding concerns of the Committee of which Konvitz was a member (November 1960). Routine personal correspondence with Charles Desmond, Chief Judge of the State of New York Court of Appeals. Correspondence with Elliot B. Doft in which Konvitz elucidates the history of Jewish students and faculty at Cornell (October 11, 1962). Correspondence with Judge Mary H. Donlon, United States Customs Court. Donlon responds to a letter from Doctor Konvitz passing along a query from Morris Bishop as to the origin of the idea that the Industrial and Labor Relations School should be established as one of the contract colleges at Cornell. Donlon responds in detail (December 17, 1962). Other routine personal correspondence with Donlon. Correspondence with Justice William O. Douglas, United States Supreme Court, regarding brief, and comments on publications (1952-1956). Correspondence with Rabbi Samuel H. Dresner, Editor of Conservative Judaism, and Doctor Abraham Duker, Yeshiva University and former President of the College of Jewish Studies in Chicago, regarding routine scholarly and personal matters.
  - D - General Correspondence, 1961-1980 (Box 11, Folder 27)
    1961-1964, 1966-1967, 1970-1972, 1974-1980. Correspondence with Jack J. diamond, a member of the United Hebrew Immigrant Aid Society staff, regarding work being done at Cornell on migration and Diamond's own work on Israeli migration to the United States (August 4 and 12, 1966). Letter from Simcha Dinitz, Israeli Ambassador to the United States, inviting Doctor Konvitz to attend a private meeting with Yitzhak Rabin, Prime Minister of Israel (January 20, 1976). Correspondence with United States Senator Bob Dole regarding Konvitz's views on a number of bills concerning the limitation of police power with regard to privacy interests and on the Supreme Court's decision in Zucher versus Stanford Daily (June 29, 1978). Konvitz favors Dole's Bill, S. 3222 (July 24, 1978). Correspondence with Professor Norman Dorsen, Chairman of the American Civil Liberties Union and professor at New York University Law School. Dorsen notes that Konvitz is mentioned in the biography of Roger Baldwin as one of the early American Civil Liberties Union leaders (December 14, 1976). Dorsen asks Professor Konvitz if he can help in interesting graduating Cornell law students in applying for New York University graduate student grants for work in civil liberties (October 2, 1962). Correspondence with Congressman Thomas J. Downey, United States House of Representatives, regarding academic concerns at the West Point Military Academy. Letter from Congressman Robert F. Drinan, United States House of Representatives, thanking Konvitz for his views with regard to the Copyright Bill, H.R. 2223, which is before a Subcommittee of which Drinan is a member. Drinan comments that he has been impressed by the testimony of the publishers and others who have insisted that the definition of "fair use" as understood in the copyright law not be changed as opposed to the arguments of educators and librarians who want the understanding of "fair use" expanded (July 25, 1975). Personal correspondence with Doctor Alexander Dushkin, Institute of Contemporary Correspondence with Justice Edward R. Dudley, Supreme Court of New York, regarding the status of the Liberian Codification Project (November 9, 1978).
  - Damage Suits Against Unions [Material in a transfer file], 1962-1963 (Box 11, Folder 28)
    Memorandum to Konvitz from D.E. Cullen regarding the possibility of getting support from a foundation to complete the damage suit manuscript (September 18, 1962)
  - Day, Edmund E., 1946-1950 (Box 11, Folder 29)
    1946-1948, 1950. Correspondence with President Edmund E. Day, Cornell University. Konvitz agrees to serve on the committee concerned with the development and construction of the World War II Memorial Building to serve as an Interfaith Center and headquarters for the Cornell United Religious Works (November 2 and 3, 1948). Correspondence regarding the presentation of Sabine Festschrift to Professor Sabine. Konvitz, in a confidential letter, brought to Day's attention the comments of Doctor Felix S. Cohen, the Assistant Solicitor of the Department of the Interior, regarding the challenge to the validity of the will of a Puerto Rican resident who died willing some hundreds of thousands of dollars to Cornell University, by the leader of the local bar, Felix Ochoteca, on behalf of heirs or alleged heirs. Konvitz also passed on to Day biographical material included by Cohen [see Box 10, file 23 for the letter from Cohen to Konvitz] (November 13, 1947). Other personal correspondence.
  - De Capriles, Miguel A., 1946-1956 (Box 11, Folder 30)
    1946-1950, 1953, 1956. Correspondence with Associate Dean Miguel A. Capriles, New York University School of Law, regarding the chapters of the book, Latin-American Legal Philosophy, that Konvitz, de Capriles, and Hayzus cooperated in getting translated. Also correspondence regarding routine personal and professional matters.
  - Dewey, John, 1949 (Box 11, Folder 31)
    A personal letter to Professor Konvitz from John Dewey thanking Konvitz for his review of Dewey's last book in the Reconstructionist. Dewey also praises the articles in the issue of the magazine with Konvitz's review. Also a notice that includes Konvitz's participation on a Philosophy Club Phi Delta Kappa panel discussion on John Dewey's contribution to philosophy, his impact on education, and his philosophy of freedom. Other routine announcements.
  - Dince, Robert R., Junior., 1948-1959 (Box 11, Folder 32)
    1948-1950, 1953-1959. Personal correspondence with Professor Robert Dince, University of Georgia College of Business Administration. Dince is married to Konvitz's niece. In his letters Dince discusses his impressions of Georgia, the University of Georgia, and the race relations in the South and at the University.
  - Dince, Robert, 1961-1979 (Box 11, Folder 33)
    1961-1963, 1965-1968, 1975, 1977-1979. Personal Correspondence with Professor Robert Dince, Head of the Department of Bank and Finance at the University of Georgia. Konvitz mentions in a letter that while he is in Israel, in addition to lecturing at Hebrew University, he will advise the University on founding a department of labor studies and engage in some activities for the Histadrut and the Ministry of Labor (May 16, 1961). Dince, who knows former President Carter and Doctor Alfred Kahn, describes some of his impressions of political life in Washington (April 17, 1979). In other letters, Dince discusses race relations at the University of Georgia and in the South. He also discusses some of the financial, academic, and social aspects of the University.
  - Dropsie College, 1958-1979 (Box 11, Folder 34)